<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Writing | tim tregubov]]></title>
  <link href="http://timofei7.github.com/blog/categories/writing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://timofei7.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-27T18:19:51-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://timofei7.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[timofei7]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[a paper: The Neural Mechanisms and Purposes of Randomness in Consciousness]]></title>
    <link href="http://timofei7.github.com/blog/2010/06/08/a-paper-the-neural-mechanisms-and-purposes-of-randomness-in-consciousness/"/>
    <updated>2010-06-08T01:21:36-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://timofei7.github.com/blog/2010/06/08/a-paper-the-neural-mechanisms-and-purposes-of-randomness-in-consciousness</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you believe in free will or determinism?   Either way,  imagine you are
creating a life form, and that you want it to have free will.  You figure out
that you need to design an organ that would be responsible for this.  You
decide to call it the "free willer".</p>

<p>What would this organ do? You realize that it must make decisions, as that is
what "will" allows you to do.  But how will it do so?  You realize that
learning is involved -- that this organ needs to take into consideration past
events. Oops, you have just created the deterministic willer!</p>

<p>Ok ok, let's back up a minute.  If we don't take into consideration past
events... well then the decisions it would make would have to be random.  Is
that what we want? Not really, random decisions won't get this new life form
very far!</p>

<p>What other decision mechanisms could we come up with for this organ?  Well it
could be influenced by some predetermined set of rules or genes that get
better over time, but that's just another determinism!</p>

<p>Ideally what we want is something that is influenced by past events
(learning). Something that can improve its programming over generations
(genes). And finally something that can decide to do OTHER than its
deterministic inputs dictate (the free part).</p>

<p>Turns out that the brain marries randomness with learning and genes in a
perfect way to achieve just this!  We already have an organ that will
purposefully introduce randomness into our thinking process so that we can
come up with unique solutions and choices that are not predetermined by the
universe or by our genes and past experiences (at least not exclusively).</p>

<p>Here's a paper I wrote about this that goes into this in more detail.  The
brain is sooo cool.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><strong>AI Randomness </strong><br/>
The field of computer artificial intelligence often finds algorithms that use
randomness extremely useful. Simulated annealing, genetic algorithms, random
walk, stochastic algorithms and neural networks, cryptography, random
constraint satisfaction, and even the common quicksort all employ randomness
to some degree or another (Russel, S. J., Norvig, P., 2003). Randomness is
often used to get an algorithm unstuck or to allow an algorithm to find an
approximate solution much quicker than it would take to find an optimal one
(finding the optimal solution in large state spaces is very often simply not
computationally feasible).</p>

<p>For instance, in simulated annealing a local search algorithm will randomly
choose among nearby solutions in an effort to prevent getting stuck at a local
optimum (ibid., pg 120). A local search algorithm is an algorithm that changes
the current state (or states) based on information it knows about surrounding
states rather than exhaustively searching down paths from a start state. A
simple example of this is the hill climbing algorithm (ibid., pg.122). The
algorithm simply examines positions in the search space adjacent to it's
current position and picks the better one. When nothing adjacent is better it
stops. However, stopping at this point does not necessarily imply the best
solution: this might be the top of a small hill that is next to a big
mountain. To make this algorithm not get stuck at local maxima, whenever it
gets to the top (since we are talking about climbing), instead of claiming
victory it should attempt a random jump to another location, but remember the
last highest peak. This way after some number of maximum random jumps the
algorithm will either find the global optimal or the best it could find in the
given time. The physics annealing analog is repeatedly heating a metal (to
progressively less high temperatures) and allowing to cool in between cycles
to align the crystalline structure into continually smaller-finer crystals.
Thus instead of simply randomly jumping the algorithm could assign a lowering
probability for each step as it jumps to avoid jumping too far as it narrows
in on the actual optimum (ibid., pg 124).</p>

<p>Genetic algorithms (and stochastic beam search on which they are based) can be
explained in terms of evolution. In stochastic beam search a greedy local
search such as hillclimbing is run some n number of times in parallel. At each
step, n of the best possible successors are chosen at random with a decreasing
probability assigned to each given its value (provided by some heuristic value
function) and the current time step. The biological analogy to this is natural
selection. Each successor state is an offspring of a parent state organism and
the successors are selected based on their fitness. Genetic algorithms take
this a step further by combining two parent states analogously to sexual
reproduction. They are similar to stochastic beam search except with the
addition of a few steps that deal with crossing the 'genes' of the parent
states. States are usually stored as sequences of characters or numbers and
after being crossed are also randomly mutated.</p>

<p>These are just a few examples of randomness in AI computing. These are fairly
simple examples however, a larger problem for AI is what to do when the world
is complex and uncertain. Simulated annealing and stochastic beam search are
part of the Monte Carlo family of algorithms that use randomness to help deal
with uncertainty in large numbers of inputs. Any large scale modeling with
uncertain inputs requires probabilistic reasoning which often requires
randomness to deal with any sort of large connected network (ibid., 530).</p>

<p>In these algorithms, randomness plays a part, however the other essential part
is probability. Without probabilistic reasoning, no complex modeling, learning
or planning given uncertain inputs could be possible (ibid., 480). Bayesian
networks are perhaps the most famous of probabilistic tools used to compute
the probabilities of unknown variables using networks of connected
probabilities. At the neuronal level in the physical brain probability plays a
big role. The research areas most clearly connecting AI to the human brain are
artificial neural networks.</p>

<p>Artificial neural networks can have a fairly simple mathematical model. A
neural network is composed of units connected to each other. Each connection
has a weight which not only carries the 'strength' of the connection but also
whether it is excitatory or inhibitory (the numerical weight is signed). Each
node has inputs (which are summed), an activation function (either a hard
threshold or a sigmoid) and output links to other nodes (ibid., 728). After
training, an artificial neural network can not only encode complex boolean
operations but also can function as short term memory (if connected as a
recurrent network with reafferent loops). The significance of this model is
that although it is quite simplified, it shows a probabilistic network
analogous to the neural network of the cortex.</p>

<p><strong>Probabilistic Neurons</strong><br/>
Since the brain's neuronal circuitry is the basis for artificial neural
networks, there are clear parallels even though the actual system is much more
complicated than the computational model. The weights can be conveyed not only
by width of the synaptic gap (usually around one forty-thousandth of a
millimeter (Penrose, R., 1989)) but more importantly by the timing of the
axonal pulses (Freeman, W. J., 2000, pg. 41). The presynaptic electrical
axonal pulse has a constant current height and so the strength of the signal
is conveyed by the rate of the pulses. The dendrite of the postsynaptic neuron
(via the action of neurotransmitters in the synaptic cleft) integrates these
pulses into a amplitude modulated wave input for the postsynaptic neuron. The
various currents from the dendrites on the postsynaptic neuron are summed up
in the trigger zone near the nucleus of the neuron. That current is what
triggers the neuron and is capable of being measured as potential in an
electroencephalogram (EEG) (ibid., pg. 42). If the current reaches the action
potential then the neuron will trigger it's own axonal pulses. The axonal
pulses take some time to travel but there is no attenuation of the signal --
this is essential to be able to transmit values over long distances without
losing energy. Dendrite current modulation is different -- it is able to
integrate with currents from other dendrites in the cell body current loop.
This enables the summing of potentials (ibid., pg. 46). One thing to note
about the pulse-width conversion (ibid, pg. 46) is that it is not stepped or
linear but rather sigmoid (leaning s) shaped. Slow at low and high activation
but increasing linearly in the middle. By this action the neuron reacts
differently to incoming pulses given its current state.</p>

<p>Some neurons have leaky terminal membranes allowing a slow change in potential
(Burns, B.D, 1968, pg. 23) . This causes them to fire at random intervals.
Taken alone this periodic random firing does not amount to much, however given
the density of neuronal connections, it is useful to also consider the action
of groups of neurons rather than single individuals. A noticeable group effect
that occurs is subthreshold oscillation. For each neuron to stay alive it
needs to periodically activate (Freeman, W. J., 2000, pg. 41). There appear to
be synchronization waves that result in periodic rises in subthreshold
membrane neuron potential. These result from a collective pattern of recurrent
excitation and inhibition from interneurons (shorter local reach neurons
(ibid., pg 39) (Buzsaki, G., 2006). Not every neuron fires every time but
collectively there is an oscillation pattern. This oscillation constrains the
times during which neurons may fire and thus produces a synchronizing effect
(Buzsaki, G., 2006, pg. 76). Neuronal firing often needs to be synchronized to
produce the desired effect -- if two neurons fire and if, because of the
oscillation, the probability that they will fire simultaneously is increased,
they are more likely to push a third neuron over it's activation threshold. If
the neural process is widely distributed and complex then the synchronicity
becomes even more important in it's constraint of timing differences because
of distance (ibid., pg. 115). There are several different oscillation
frequencies ranging from multiple seconds to 600hz. Since they temporally
constrain neural firing the different frequencies have different
purposes/ranges. Fast oscillation is more appropriate for local, small
distance neural patterns whereas slower clock speeds allow neurons further
apart to cooperate. Additionally the oscillations are not constant, they are
perpetually attracting and repelling each other as they do not have any stable
phase relationship. Thus, they interfere with each other, but that chaos and
fluctuation may be a necessary part of the temporal organization of the brain
as a whole. All of this oscillation can be seen as noise, not only because the
neurons are firing without any external stimuli but also because the
relationship between all the different oscillation frequencies is <em>e</em> (2.71),
the natural logarithm -- this results in a chaotic pattern that appears like
"pink" noise on an EEG (ibid., pg. 113). "Pink" noise is also known as complex
noise -- this is because its power ratio is 1/<em>f</em>, meaning that the amplitude
of the waves decreases as the frequency increases. Although to a physicist
this would simply suggest that it is a noisy system, what appears as noise is
also a chaotic yet functional synchronizer and organizer of neuron systems
(ibid., 119). The same neurons participate in multiple rhythms, and the
oscillating groups can change and influence each other.</p>

<blockquote><p>The brain not only gives rise to large-scale, long-term patterns, but these
self-organized collective patterns also govern the behavior of its constituent
neurons. The firing patterns of single cells depend not only on their
instantaneous external inputs but also on the history of their firing patterns
and the state of the network into which they are embedded (Buzsaki, G., 2006,
pg 122).</p></blockquote>

<p>However, these collective patterns are transient, they fluctuate around
different brain areas, organizing temporal information where needed on
specific time-scales depending on how large of a neuronal pattern is needed.
"Transient order emerges from halfway between order and disorder from the
territory of complexity" (ibid., pg 135).</p>

<p>It turns out that the power ratio of the pink noise also happens to fit the
data for other time-related brain tasks: forgetting, habituation, music and
speech. The brain is not competing with its own noise, it is in essence
harnessing the noise as multiple dynamic timing devices synchronizing
particular groups of neurons for specific tasks at specific clock rates.
Indeed because of this very action, and the fact that neurons are strongly
interconnected (some pyramidal cells can have thousands of dendrite
connections sites (Buzsaki, G., 2006, pg. 32)), even small local perturbations
can become amplified and spread throughout the network.</p>

<p>This amplification is of great importance. Consider a neuron that is almost
ready to fire, but does not quite have enough current to reach it's action
potential. A noise input could cause it to fire when it otherwise would not
have. Because the noise is stochastic, the neuron's firing is not
deterministic. It may or may not fire depending on the noise in the system
around it. Small weak local signals can become noticeable when the noise bumps
it up. Additionally small periodic signals can act as attractors to the noise
oscillation and can in effect draw attention to themselves by pulling the
oscillation frequency toward their own.</p>

<p>Given these mechanisms it is evident that neuronal firing is probabilistic.
Even sensory neurons such as the ganglion cells in the retina have been shown
to have unpredictable responses (Burns, B.D, 1968, pg 28). This behavior is of
interest because it allows for a break with deterministic, simple input-output
machine operation and allows a greater uncertainty to exist.</p>

<p><strong>Brownian Motion</strong><br/>
Another source of uncertainty in the brain could be brownian motion. Brownian
motion is the basis for brownian noise. Brownian noise is also called random
walk noise and has a power density ratio of 1/<em>f</em> 2 (Buzsaki, G., 2006, pg.
121). It gets its name from brownian motion. Brownian motion was originally
discovered by Robert Brown, a biologist, who noticed that particles of pollen
on the surface of water will move around erratically (Nelson, E., 1967, pg.
11). The concept was later further worked on by Einstein who in part used it
to prove the existence of atoms. The basic idea is that a larger particle
surrounded by a myriad of smaller particles suspended in a liquid or gas that
all have their own movement will be pushed around by the motion of the smaller
particles in a random fashion. Brownian motion over longer periods/distances
is random, but can be predicted at short intervals by the average velocity and
density of the molecules in the suspension (Buzsaki, G., 2006, pg. 121). It
has been shown that brownian motion applies to all biological systems, "as a
result of thermal agitation processes, molecules are constantly on the move,
colliding with each other and bouncing back and forth" (Marguet, D., Lenne,
PF., Rigneault, H., He, HT., 2006, pg. 288). On a macroscopic level however
brownian motion is a diffusion process.</p>

<blockquote><p>Diffusion processes have the following main features:  (1) the diffusion
rates are temperature-depen- dent, (2) as collisions with other molecules slow
down diffusion processes, the higher the molecular density of a medium is, the
lower the diffusion rate will be and most importantly, (3) as the random
forces generated by collisions have no preferred direction, diffusion will
cause a tendency towards homogeneity. (ibid., pg. 288)</p></blockquote>

<p>Marguet et al suggest that any variability in activation of the postsynaptic
neuron would be due purely to "stochastic variations in basic presynaptic
elements, such as the vesicle volume, the vesicle docking position, and the
vesicle neurotransmitter concentration" (ibid., pg. 298) rather than any
variability due to brownian motion. So although brownian motion is used as a
diffusion process and is certainly harnessed by the brain to effect homogenous
dispersal of neurotransmitters in the synaptic cleft, it is not responsible
directly for any variability in actual neuronal firing.</p>

<p><strong>Quantum Theories</strong><br/>
There are many theories involving consciousness and quantum theory. The
problems with these theories is that the brain is too hot to be susceptible to
any currently known quantum effects. There is too much classical noise and
complexity for a single quanta to have any effect at all. A single cell in the
retina may react to a single photon (which would be a quantum event) however
our brains need at least seven neurons to react to actually perceive it
(Penrose, R, 1989, pg. 516). Additionally, most neurons in the brain require
many neurotransmitters to trigger many sodium or chloride channels to open
which in turn could trigger the neuron to fire. This would require too many
quanta to be useful. However, theories abound of either undiscovered cells
that respond to single quanta or computational complexity that can only be
solved by quantum computation. Additionally there are dualist theories that a
mental energy influences the physical brain through quantum effects. These
theories attempt to escape from determinism and provide a explanation why free
will is non-determined. Christoff Koch (2006) provides an eloquent rebuttal of
quantum theories, for now at least:</p>

<blockquote><p>The content of consciousness is rich and highly differentiated. It is
associated with the firing activity of a very large number of neurons spread
all over the cortex and associated satellites, such as the thalamus. Thus, any
one conscious percept or thought must be expressed in a wide- flung coalition
of neurons firing together. Even if quantum gates exist within the confines of
neurons, it remains totally nebulous how information of relevance to the
organism would get to these quantum gates. Moreover, how would it be kept
coherent across the milli- and centimeters separating individual neurons when
synaptic and spiking processes, the primary means of neuronal communication
on the perceptual timescale, destroy quantum information?</p></blockquote>

<p>It is far more likely that the material basis of consciousness can be
understood within a purely neurobiological framework, without invoking any
quantum-mechanical deus ex machina. (Koch, C., 2006).</p>

<p><strong>Consciousness</strong><br/>
How do these various theories relate to consciousness? Randomness can be, at
least partially, an escape from determinism. If every neuron firing were
physically determined then there is no way that we as as 'free agent' could
have chosen differently from how we did choose. This breaks a mandate of 'free
will': we are free to have chosen differently from how we did choose. However,
going too far toward randomness would break the other mandate of 'free will':
our actions belong to us and reflect who we are (and that our actions are not
simply random). A middle ground would surprisingly satisfy both of these
criteria and allow a free will that is both based on our past experiences but
is not tied down to them deterministically. If the system is probabilistic,
then at any point we can say both, "I could have done differently," and "I
chose that way based on my past experiences, based on who I am." At least
semantically this fulfills the requirements of free will. Additionally, it is
hard to imagine what third rule would invalidate this solution and would at
the same time define the concept of free will in such a way as to keep the
common intuition of what it is. Wegner in "The Illusion of Conscious Will"
poses a thought experiment of inventing a Free Willer -- an organ that makes
free will choices. Such an instrument cannot ignore past experiences as that
would be meaningless, and it cannot be purely random as that is equally
meaningless. How do the various sources and types of randomness affect the
free will problem?</p>

<p>AI randomness is an example of how randomness is useful purely
computationally. AI algorithms attempt, at least in part, to make sense of a
complex uncertain world and to make internal models of it and for this they
need randomness. This does not imply that the human brain requires randomness
in the same way however.</p>

<p>The probabilistic nature of neuronal firing and the noise of oscillation
appears very promising however. Not only is a neuron not guaranteed to fire
when presented with some stimuli, but it may also fire randomly when presented
with stimuli that should be too weak. This creates an instability in the
system allowing alternative solutions and unpredictable effects. Rodolfo
Llinas (2003) goes even further to claim that conscious experience is created
by the temporal organization provided by oscillatory synchronization.</p>

<p>Quantum effects could provide a very interesting source of uncertainty in the
brain, but unfortunately there is no current reason to think that that it
does.</p>

<p><strong>Conclusions</strong><br/>
It appears from this summary of some of the primary randomness theories that
indeed there are some sources of randomness in the brain. However, not all of
these sources are useful for a discussion of consciousness. For instance, no
solid proof exists for quantum effects in the brain. Brownian motion in the
synapse is useful for diffusion but not specifically for volition or free
will. However oscillation and pink noise provide an interesting systemic
effect that should not be overlooked. If this noise is truly stochastic and
unpredictable enough it provides a middle ground between the two opposites of
randomness and determinism and allow us to feel that our decisions are our
own.</p>

<hr />

<p><strong>References:</strong> Burns, B. D. (1968). The uncertain nervous system. London: Arnold.<br/>
Buzsáki, G. (2006). Rhythms of the brain. Oxford; New York: Oxford University
Press.</p>

<p>Freeman, A., Libet, B., &amp; Sutherland, K. (1999). The volitional brain :Towards
a neuroscience of free will. Thorverton: Imprint Academic.</p>

<p>Freeman, W. J. (2000; 1999). How brains make up their minds. New York:
Columbia University Press.</p>

<p>Hutcheon, B., &amp; Yarom, Y. (2000). Resonance, oscillation and the intrinsic
frequency preferences of neurons. Trends in Neurosciences, 23(5), 216-222.
doi:DOI: 10.1016/S0166-2236(00)01547-2</p>

<p>Koch, C., &amp; Hepp, K. (2006). Quantum mechanics in the brain. Nature,
440(7084), 611-611. Retrieved from http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/440611a</p>

<p>Llinás, R. (2003). Consciousness and the thalamocortical loop. International
Congress Series, 1250, 409-416. doi:DOI: 10.1016/S0531-5131(03)01067-7</p>

<p>Marguet, D., Lenne, P., Rigneault, H., &amp; He, H. (2006). Dynamics in the plasma
membrane: How to combine fluidity and order. The EMBO Journal, 25(15),
3446-3457. Retrieved fromhttp://dx.doi.org/10.1038/sj.emboj.7601204</p>

<p>Nelson, E. (1967). Dynamical theories of brownian motion. Princeton, N.J.:
Princeton University Press.</p>

<p>Osaka, N. (2003). Neural basis of consciousness. Philadelphia, PA: John
Benjamins Pub.</p>

<p>Penrose, R. (1989). The emperor's new mind :Concerning computers, minds, and
the laws of physics. Oxford; New York: Oxford University Press.</p>

<p>Russell, S. J., &amp; Norvig, P. (2003). Artificial intelligence :A modern
approach (2nd ed.). Upper Saddle River, N.J.: Prentice Hall/Pearson Education.</p>

<p>Ventriglia, F., &amp; Di Maio, V. (2002). Stochastic fluctuations of the synaptic
function. Biosystems, 67(1-3), 287-294. doi:DOI: 10.1016/S0303-2647(02)00086-2</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[why the DLPFC is the coolest part of the brain]]></title>
    <link href="http://timofei7.github.com/blog/2010/04/30/why-the-dlpfc-is-the-coolest-part-of-the-brain/"/>
    <updated>2010-04-30T01:33:47-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://timofei7.github.com/blog/2010/04/30/why-the-dlpfc-is-the-coolest-part-of-the-brain</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>want to learn about why the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex is the coolest part
of the brain?</p>

<!--more-->


<p><strong>The DLPFC</strong><br/>
With the onset of modern neuroscience a common question often discussed is:
where in the brain are self-regulation, executive control, free will,
volition, selection, short-term memory, attention, planning, and overall
consciousness located and by what neurological processes do they occur. The
prime brain areas that is thought to be responsible are the frontal lobes.
However a problem is presented when studying this area in humans: comparison
to monkey's brains has been difficult as the PFC, prefrontal cortex, is
structured somewhat differently (Petrides, M., Pandya, D.N., 1999 and Fuster,
J. M., 2008. pg. 21) and thus comparisons can be complicated, and invasive
techniques are largely limited to non-humans. Lesion studies have sometimes
led to seemingly contradicting results that are hotly debated. However
researchers agree that the prefrontal cortex as a whole is the essential area
responsible for higher behavioral functions. One of the essential brain areas
associated with these psychological processes is the DLPFC, dorsolateral
prefrontal cortex. This area appears to be critical for working memory,
planning, selective attention, temporal integration and volition.</p>

<p><strong>Location and Structure</strong><br/>
The DLPFC is located in the middle frontal gyrus and is typically defined
cytoarchitectonicaly as Brodmann areas 46 and 9 (Berntson, G. G., &amp; Cacioppo,
J. T., 2009, pg. 586). BA8 is also sometimes considered the posterior DLPFC or
simply adjacent to it (Miller, Earl K., Cohen, Jonathan D., 2001, pg. 169).
The DLPFC is one of the last areas in humans to develop and myelinate as the
brain myelinates back to front (Fuster, J. M., 2008. pg. 15).</p>

<p>C<strong>onnections</strong></p>

<p>A critical aspect of the DLPFC is that it is extraordinarily interconnected
with other brain areas and is the most connected of all the PFC areas. It is
connected to sensory and motor cortexes as well as interconnected with other
PFC areas.</p>

<p><strong>Sensory Cortex Connections</strong><br/>
BA46 and BA9 have connections to the visual, somatosensory and auditory
projections via the occipital, parietal and temporal cortices. Both areas are
also connected to the multimodal rostral superior temporal sulcus with neurons
responding to multi-sensory inputs. (Miller, Earl K., Cohen, Jonathan D.,
2001). The posterior parietal cortex in particular plays a large role in that
it is both a mutli-modal area and is related to spatial working memory,
attention. It has also been implicated in having a role in intention (Libet et
al, 1999).</p>

<p><strong>Motor Cortex Connections</strong><br/>
BA46 is particularly connected to pre-motor areas; it has connections to the
SMA, the pSMA, the rostral cingulate, the lateral frontal pre-motor cortex and
to the cerebellum and superior colliculus ( Miller, E. K., Cohen, J. D., 2001.
pg. 175). BA46 also sends projections to the BA8 frontal eye fields and
indirectly receives inputs, along with the all of the prefrontal cortex, from
the basal ganglia (pg. 175).</p>

<p><strong>Prefrontal Interconnections</strong><br/>
All of the prefrontal areas are interconnected to a large degree. BA46 and BA9
are both connected to the orbital and medial prefrontal areas (BA 10,
11,13,14) as well as to each other. BA9 is connected to the ventrolateral
areas (BA 12,45). BA8 connects to BA46. These interconnections not only allow
indirect communication to other systems that are connected to other prefrontal
areas (such as the limbic system through the medial PFC areas), but also
provides a way for disperse systems to be indirectly wired together through
this central area. The convergence of cortico-cortical pathways suggests that
part of the DLPFC's operation is as a cross-modal area of association (Fuster,
J. M., 2008. pg. 34).</p>

<p><strong>Experimental Connections</strong><br/>
An experiment that supports this prefrontal interconnectedness theory (Tomita
et al, 2001) studied top-down communication from the prefrontal cortex to the
inferior temporal cortex (which has been shown to store long-term visual
memories (Miyashita, Y., 1993)). The inferior temporal cortex receives visual
input contra-laterally from the occipital lobe and the two sides are sub-
cortically connected. In this experiment two monkeys were given split visual
stimuli and were trained to associate certain cues with categories of stimuli.
Then the connection between the inferior temporal cortices was severed -- to
theoretically prevent a cue presented to the ipsilateral side (the side that
did not see the choice) from activating a category recall on the contralateral
side. The bottom-up condition was when both the cue and the choice were
offered to the same contralateral vision field, and the top-down condition was
when the cue was offered on the ipsilateral side while the choice was offered
on the contralateral side. The results, measured via single neuron recordings,
showed that when the direct connection between the sides of the inferior
temporal lobe was severed there was a delay in recall but that the ipsilateral
side never-the-less showed correct activation. This experiment suggests that
the visual information travelled through the prefrontal cortex connections. To
confirm this finding the connections to the prefrontal cortex from the
inferior temporal cortex lobes were severed and only then did the monkeys fail
the task.</p>

<p><strong>Functionality</strong><br/>
Given the strong interconnectedness of all the prefrontal areas, it is no
surprise that a compartmentalization of each cytoarchitectonic area would be
an oversimplification (Fuster, J. M., 2008. pg. 6). All these areas work
together to achieve its various executive functions. However, these areas do
have discernable specializations and the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex in
particular has a number of fortes including basic working memory, cross-
temporal/modal integration, temporal ordering, planning, acting and rule
encoding, selective attention, will and volition.</p>

<p><strong>Working Memory</strong><br/>
It is commonly agreed that the lateral prefrontal cortex plays a large role in
working memory (Curtis, C. E, D'Esposito, M., 2004). However, precisely how it
works and what role the DLPFC plays in it is disputed. Special types of
neurons called memory neurons are certainly necessary if not sufficient.
Memory neurons are neurons that in a delay task appear to activate during the
delay period between a presentation and a recall of a stimuli. Some activate
during the stimulus, others right after, and even others stay active for a
while. The DLPFC has more memory neurons than any other prefrontal area
(Fuster, J. M., 2008. pg. 247). As a side note, the Frontal Eye Fields -- area
8 -- contains memory cells that are particularly attuned for eye saccades to
cued locations, whereas in areas 46 and 9 there is some evidence for memory
neuron specialization toward spatial tasks. There are however memory neurons
in many other areas of the brain, including the thalamus, inferotemporal
cortex and basal ganglia, but those memory neurons appear to be specialized
toward the sensory task of the particular area, whereas in the prefrontal
cortex the memory neurons are more multi-modal. The simple existence of memory
neurons is not enough to show the DLPFC's role in working memory.</p>

<p>Working memory as a function of the DLPFC has been primarily shown via delay
tasks with either lesion patients or appropriately trained animals with
ablations/lesions or reversible lesions via cooling. Commonly a delay task
will begin with the representation of a cue. The cue informs the participant
about a choice that is to be made later (usually the location of a salient
item such as food). Then the cue is covered up for some amount of time: the
delay period. Following this a choice is presented -- the correct choice being
informed by the cue presented prior to the delay. In many studies of animals,
when the delay is non-existent or very short, the DLPFC lesioned animals
perform normally, but as the delay increases so success at the task drops
(Fuster, J. M., 2008. pg. 144). Similar tasks however that do not have any
spatial element have shown no difference in some experiments.</p>

<p>These lesion studies lead to the theory that the DLPFC is particularly
important for spatial working memory. However there remain questions as to
what role the DLPFC plays in working memory. The interconnectedness of the
DLPFC plays a vital role in its working memory functionality. A study of the
interaction of the DLPFC and other brain areas (Fuster, J. M., Bauer, R. H., &amp;
Jervey, J. P., 1985) shows working memory to be more than a few memory neurons
but a distributed representational network encompassing many brain areas. In
particular it reveals the DLPFC as a top-down moderator of "online" working
memory tasks. The study used a Peltier chip to cool down the DLPFC and the
inferotemporal cortex in turn. Single neuron recording was used to record the
activity of memory neurons sensitive to certain colors in the inferotemporal
cortex. The monkeys were trained in a color match delay task. As they
performed the task the color sensitive neurons in the inferotemporal cortex
would activate on the working memory of the cue color. However, when the DLPFC
was cooled the firing rate of the inferotemporal neurons related to the
working memory of the task would attenuate and the animal, additionally, would
not be able to perform the task. This suggests a modulation effect from the
DLPFC to the inferotemporal cortex, where the sensory memory for this
particular task was represented, at least in part. This experiment was also
performed in reverse: the inferotemporal cortex cooled and the DLPFC activity
measured during the same delay task. The results were very similar: there was
a modulation effect in addition to lowered task performance. Fuster makes the
supposition that the model for working memory is that of,</p>

<blockquote><p>"a frontal substrate of executive memory cooperating with other brain
structures, cortical and subcortical, for the maintenance of working memory.
The function of working memory would be distributed, much as its neural
substrate, albeit under a degree of prefrontal executive -- or 'top-down'
--control." (Fuster, J. M., 2008. pg. 251)</p></blockquote>

<p>Reverberating reentry is the method by which these cortico-cortical/cortico-
subcortical memory loops are maintained neurologically (pg. 252). Projections
to and from posterior sensory cortices and the DLPFC reverberate back and
forth, each moderating and resubmitting the memory back into the loop as
needed. The theory outlined by Fuster (pg. 296) is that the DLPFC is involved
in the selection and maintenance of working memory and that the
representational aspect of any particular memory requires the brain areas
which are specialized to the sensory features of that memory.</p>

<p>There have been many PET and fMRI studies that have localized spatial working
memory to the DLPFC especially in monkeys, however in human studies not only
has it been harder to pinpoint some studies seem to suggest that the DLPF's
role is quite more elaborate and involved.</p>

<p><strong>Cross-Temporal Integration</strong><br/>
It has already been demonstrated that the DLPFC has a particular importance in
temporal integration. Simple recognition tasks without a delay do not appear
to trigger the DLPFC. Additionally, as already mentioned, the greater the
delay the more a DLPFC lesion causes impairment. Several studies show DLPFC
lesioned monkeys</p>

<blockquote><p>"deficient at tasks in which temporal frequency, temporal order, or temporal
sequence is of the essence. [..] The dorsolateral prefrontal cortex seems most
important for the mediation of the cross-temporal contingencies, as delay
tasks require" (Fuster, J. M., 2008. pg. 145).</p></blockquote>

<p>This is not surprising as working memory is an essential component of
temporally organizing cognition and behavior.</p>

<p><strong>Cross-Modal Integration </strong><br/>
Much of the DLPFC's functionality can be attributed to how interconnected it
is. This interconnectedness however not only enables cross-temporal
integration but also cross-modal integration -- neurons that receive
projections from multiple sensory areas are the mechanism behind this.</p>

<p>Fuster demonstrated cross-modal integration with a single neuron recording
study performed on monkeys (Fuster, J. M., 2008. pg. 226). The monkeys were
trained to associate an auditory tone with a particular visual stimuli -- in
this case a color. The experiment first presented the animal with the auditory
cue and then after a delay presented two colors buttons -- the animal would
need to choose the correct one that corresponded with the learned association.
Single cell neurons were recorded in the DLPFC that responded both to the
auditory cue and to the color. Thus the sensory rule for the experimental
condition was encoded in a multi-modal association. This is a precursor to the
rule encoding functionality that the DLPFC is implicated in as well.</p>

<p><strong>Planning, Acting and Rule Encoding</strong><br/>
The DLPFC is essential to the "ability to maintain any memory, recent or
remote, in the active state for the prospective performance of a goal-directed
act" (Fuster, J. M., 2008. pg. 146). Performance of a goal directed act
requires planning for the act and acting on in the plan. Related to this is
the ability to encode the rules that may be required for the task. The
beginnings of rule encoding are in the cross-modal associative abilities of
the DLPFC.</p>

<p>A recent study showed that even abstract mathematical rules can be encoded in
the DLPFC (Bongard, S., &amp; Nieder, A., 2010). The monkeys were trained to
distinguish numerosities with greater and less than rules. The stimuli were
varied and so the monkeys were unable to build concrete associative relations
between specific numbers. Using single cell recordings the study found that
there were neurons that fired specifically when a rule-indicating cue appeared
and during the application of that specific rule. The suggestion here is not
that numerosity itself is encoded in the DLPFC rather only the selection of
choosing greater or less than as rules for executive control. Numerosity
itself is a function of the posterior parietal cortex. It is also important to
note that the DLPFC abstracts rules only when the task surpasses some basic
difficulty.</p>

<p>White and Wise in a 1999 study showed that DLPFC neurons were involved in
rules involving both spatial and non-spatial cues with specific eye movements
and hand gestures. As in many of these sorts of studies, using single cell
recording, they found a significant number of neurons that were selective for
changing rules and applying them.</p>

<p>Planning is a task that is commonly associated with the prefrontal cortex in
general, but also with the DLPC in particular. A study by Morris et al in 1993
showed DLPFC activation during the tower of london task. The tower of london
is a task design to test logical planning ability and is similar to the towers
of hanoi puzzle. A common lay association with planning is internal silent
speech. A study by Ryding et al in 1996 showed DLPFC activation during silent
counting but not during counting aloud. The study attributes this activation
to the attentional component of counting internally, although it is not
obvious why there is a difference between the two in terms of attention.
Slightly more modern theories of the DLPFC may attribute this activation to
the selective goal of speaking internally or to the monitoring needs of the
feedback loop given the lack of audible feedback.</p>

<p><strong>Selective Attention and Monitoring</strong><br/>
If the DLPFC helps to maintain goal related working memory, does it also
participate in the selection and attentional aspects related to the goal as
well? An fMRI study by D'Esposito et al in 1995 seems to indicate that this
may be the case. The experiment consisted of two tasks, a spatial-rotation
task and a semantic-judgement task. When performed singly neither task
required working memory and thus did not show any DLPFC activation. However
when the tasks were to be performed simultaneously (sequentially but rapidly)
the DLPFC showed significant activation.</p>

<p>Hare et al (2009) showed that goal related decisions require DLPFC modulation
of a value signal provided/computed by the VMPFC. DLPFC activity increased in
subjects during successful self-control trails involving choosing healthy over
unhealthy-but-liked food. The experimenters suggest that this result helps
confirm the theory that the DLPFC acts via its connections to other brain
areas to promote goal-oriented behavior.</p>

<p>The DLPFC has also been shown to be activated when a task requires higher
levels of monitoring. The silent counting experiment by Ryding shows this to
some degree. Another set of tasks that shows DLPFC involvement are self-
ordered tasks. In these tasks the subject is shown a set of stimuli and then
is asked self-order them. This requires the subject to keep the memory of
which items have been selected and which have not been selected yet in working
memory and requires them to monitor those memories as they choose objects.
Petrides showed that self-ordered tasks involved DLPFC activation while
externally-ordered tasks did not (2000). Additionally he showed that the more
items were involved in the task the higher the activation regardless of
whether the stimuli were spatial or not. This result seems to indicate that
monitoring is an additional feature of the DLPFC.</p>

<p><strong>Will and Volition</strong><br/>
Given the DLPFC's role in so many aspects of "executive control" perhaps it
also has a role in the voluntary choice of actions that is so tightly
associated with the concept of consciousness.</p>

<blockquote><p>"Damage in the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex in humans leads to a lack of
spontaneous activity, distractibility by environmental cues, and the
repetitive, stereotypic use of inappropriate behavioral responses
(perseveration). These phenomena may indicate an inability to choose or
initiate the correct course of action." (Freeman, A., Libet, B., &amp; Sutherland,
K., 1999 pg. 16).</p></blockquote>

<p>Frith defines the actual act of such choosing as "a deliberate selection
[that] is subjectively experienced as willed and occurs when we have a choice
of action. [These] spontaneous or self-generated actions are not specified by
an external trigger stimulus, but are internally driven." (Frith et al, 1991).
One of the main findings on volition and the DLPFC is his PET study of word
generation and finger movements.</p>

<p>The word generation experiment consists of 3 conditions: in the first the
subject hears a list of random words and repeats each word. In the second the
subject hears words that have unambiguous opposites and must say out loud the
opposite words. The final third condition the subject hears the word "next"
and must choose a word that starts with a preset letter. The idea is that the
first two conditions are "externally specified" (Frith et al, 1991); the word
to repeat is unambiguous and no choice exists. In the third condition however
the subject must pick a word. The PET scans showed no difference in rCBF
between the first two "externally specified" conditions while the third
condition showed increased left DLPFC rCBF.</p>

<p>The finger movement part of the experiment had similar results (although rCBF
was increased bilaterally in the finger condition). The conditions were
similar: in the first the subject had one of two fingers tapped and they had
to raise that same finger in response, in the second they had to raise the
opposite, and in the third free-willed condition they had to choose which
finger to raise.</p>

<p>One problem with the word generation part of this experiment is that there is
a small working memory component -- that of keeping the already stated
previous word in mind. However, a later study by Desmond et al in 1998,
changed the condition to involve no working memory by simply giving the
participant different word stems that required choice of completions on each
trail. This study had similar results except with fMRI. Further studies by
Libet and Jahanshahi showed that temporal choice about when to make the
movement also activated the DLPFC (Freeman, A., Libet, B., &amp; Sutherland, K.,
1999 pg. 19).</p>

<p>However the DLPFC, as has been previously mentioned, does not act alone in any
of this. In each of these tasks the DLPFC worked with other brain areas by
virtue of its interconnectedness (Freeman, A., Libet, B., &amp; Sutherland, K.,
1999 pg. 20). The conclusion may be that the DLPFC "plays a role in the
selection of action, [but] the performance of the action itself is facilitated
by 'lower' motor regions, such as SMA and basal ganglia" (pg. 21). And
furthermore, the "DLPFC seems to be involved in keeping possible action in
mind before they are executed, and selecting which one will be performed" (pg.
27).</p>

<p><strong>Disorders and Lesions</strong><br/>
What role does the DLPFC play in human disorders? Lesions of the DLPFC
contribute to a myriad of symptoms including: lack of drive and awareness
(selective attention suppressed), visuospatial neglect (FEF damage), "frontal
dynamic aphasia": reduced verbal production quality, apathy and "dysexecutive
syndrome" leading to being "incapacitated in initiating spontaneous and
deliberate action" (Fuster, J. M., 2008. pg. 198). Working memory deficits
contribute to a myriad of failures upstream including in action selection,
temporal integration, and goal oriented planning. The DLPFC is also implicated
in several neurological disorders.</p>

<p><strong>Schizophrenia</strong><br/>
Schizophrenia is commonly marked by such symptoms as poor speech, temporal
integration problems, hallucinations and lack of volitional control. A study
by Weinberger et al in 1986 showed via a PET scan study that there was a lack
of appropriate increase in DLPFC activity in schizophrenia patients while
performing the Wisconsin card sorting task, which has been shown many times to
elicit DLPFC activation. This study was later expanded on in 2002 by Meyer-
Lindenberg et al to not only using PET to study rCBF during the WCST but also
presynaptic dopamine. Their study showed an inverse correlation with reduced
DLPFC activation and increased striatal 6-FD uptake, leading to the conclusion
that dopaminergic transmission dysfunction in schizophrenia may be DLPFC
related. Since schizophrenia is characterized by, "the failure to construct
logically coherent temporal configurations (gestalts) of thought -- and
consequently of speech and behavior" (Fuster, J. M., 2008. pg. 313) -- that
precisely implicates the DLPFC in terms of working memory and temporal
integration problems.</p>

<p><strong>Conclusions</strong><br/>
A summary of DLPFC working memory involvement is provided by D'Esposito et al:</p>

<blockquote><p>When the amount of to-be-remembered information presented at the beginning
of a delayed-response trial approaches or exceeds short-term memory capacity
[...], dorsolateral PFC is preferentially engaged. Dorsolateral PFC-supported
processes may facilitate the efficient encoding of information. During the
subsequent delay interval, when no information is accessible to the subject,
both ventro- and dorsolateral PFC are recruited. If manipulation of this
information is additionally required during the delay period, dorsolateral PFC
is recruited to an additional extent. Upon the presentation of the probe
stimulus, when a subject is required to make a response based on what was
presented at the beginning of the trial, dorsolateral PFC is again engaged,
presumably as the subject scans the information that was retained across the
trial and chooses an appropriate motor response. [...] Together, the results
of these studies highlight the temporal dynamics of PFC function during
working memory task performance. (2000)</p></blockquote>

<p>However it is obvious from the DLPFC's involvement in selection and planning
and volition that its function cannot be limited to only working memory.
Selective attention is at the most basic level attention to internal
representations. These internal representations are maintained by working
memory and thus these two are closely related. Additionally planning involves
attention to future possibilities, what Ingvar (1985) called "memory of the
future", and is thus also closely related to working memory. It appears that
although there is no cohesive theory for the DLPFC, a general sense could be
that all things DLPFC are related to temporal integration across multiple
sensory modes. The interconnectedness of the DLPFC is its defining
characteristic.</p>

<hr />

<p><strong>References:</strong></p>

<p>Boller, F., Grafman, J., &amp; Holyoak, K. J. (1995). Structure and functions of the human prefrontal cortex. New York: New York Academy of Sciences. Bongard, S., &amp; Nieder, A. (2010).</p>

<p>Basic mathematical rules are encoded by primate prefrontal cortex neurons. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 107(5), 2277-2282. doi:10.1073/pnas.0909180107 Curtis, C. E., &amp; D'Esposito, M. (2004).</p>

<p>The effects of prefrontal lesions on working memory performance and theory. Cognitive, Affective, &amp; Behavioral Neuroscience, 4(4), 528-539. Retrieved from http://cabn.psychonomic-journals.org/content/4/4/528.abstract Desmond, J. E., Gabrieli, J. D. E., &amp; Glover, G. H. (1998).</p>

<p>Dissociation of frontal and cerebellar activity in a cognitive task: Evidence for a distinction between selection and search. NeuroImage, 7(4), 368-376. Retrieved from http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/B6WNP-45M2XYH-W/2/bf49e4719a18fb7a65ba16cf0b5d3547 D'Esposito, M., Detre, J. A., Alsop, D. C., Shin, R. K., Atlas, S., &amp; Grossman, M. (1995).</p>

<p>The neural basis of the central executive system of working memory. Nature, 378(6554), 279-281. Retrieved from http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/378279a0 D'Esposito, M., Postle, B. R., &amp; Rypma, B. (2000).</p>

<p>Prefrontal cortical contributions to working memory: Evidence from event-related fMRI studies.. Experimental Brain Research, 133(1), 3-11. Retrieved from http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s002210000395 D'Esposito, M., (2003).</p>

<p>Neurological foundations of cognitive neuroscience. Cambridge, Mass.: MIT Press. Retrieved from http://www.netLibrary.com/urlapi.asp?action=summary&amp;v=1&amp;bookid=78182 Freeman, A., Libet, B., &amp; Sutherland, K. (1999).</p>

<p>The volitional brain :Towards a neuroscience of free will. Thorverton: Imprint Academic. Freeman, A., Libet, B., &amp; Sutherland, K. (1999).</p>

<p>The volitional brain :Towards a neuroscience of free will. Thorverton: Imprint Academic. Frith, C. D., Friston, K., Liddle, P. F., &amp; Frackowiak, R. S. J. (1991).</p>

<p>Willed action and the prefrontal cortex in man: A study with PET. Proceedings: Biological Sciences, 244(1311), 241-246. Retrieved from http://www.jstor.org/stable/76606 Fuster, J. M. (2008).</p>

<p>The prefrontal cortex (4th ed.). Amsterdam; Boston: Academic Press/Elsevier. Fuster, J. M., Bauer, R. H., &amp; Jervey, J. P. (1985).</p>

<p>Functional interactions between inferotemporal and prefrontal cortex in a cognitive task. Brain Research, 330(2), 299-307. doi:DOI: 10.1016/0006-8993(85)90689-4 Gathercole, S. E. (1999). Cognitive approaches to the development of short-term memory. Trends in Cognitive Sciences, 3(11), 410-419. doi:DOI: 10.1016/S1364-6613(99)01388-1 Hare, T. A., Camerer, C. F., &amp; Rangel, A. (2009).</p>

<p>Self-control in decision-making involves modulation of the vmPFC valuation system. Science, 324(5927), 646-648. doi:10.1126/science.1168450 Hoshi, E. (2006).</p>

<p>Functional specialization within the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex: A review of anatomical and physiological studies of non-human primates. Neuroscience Research, 54(2), 73-84. doi:DOI: 10.1016/j.neures.2005.10.013 Meyer-Lindenberg, A., Miletich, R. S., Kohn, P. D., Esposito, G., Carson, R. E., Quarantelli, M., et al. (2002).</p>

<p>Reduced prefrontal activity predicts exaggerated striatal dopaminergic function in schizophrenia. Nature Neuroscience, 5(3), 267-271. Retrieved from http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nn804 Miller, E. K., &amp; Cohen, J. D. (2001).</p>

<p>An integrative theory of prefrontal cortex function. Annual Review of Neuroscience, 24(1), 167-202. Retrieved from http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.neuro.24.1.167 Miyashita, Y. (1993).</p>

<p>Inferior temporal cortex: Where visual perception meets memory. Annual Review of Neuroscience, 16(1), 245-263. Retrieved from http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.ne.16.030193.001333 Morris, R. G., Ahmed, S., Syed, G. M., &amp; Toone, B. K. (1993).</p>

<p>Neural correlates of planning ability: Frontal lobe activation during the tower of london test. Neuropsychologia, 31(12), 1367-1378. doi:DOI: 10.1016/0028-3932(93)90104-8 Petrides, M., &amp; Pandya, D. N. (1999).</p>

<p>Dorsolateral prefrontal cortex: Comparative cytoarchitectonic analysis in the human and the macaque brain and corticocortical connection patterns. European Journal of Neuroscience, 11(3), 1011. doi:10.1046/j.1460-9568.1999.00518.x Petrides, M. (2000).</p>

<p>The role of the mid-dorsolateral prefrontal cortex in working memory. Experimental Brain Research, 133(1), 44-54. Retrieved from http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s002210000399 Rossi, A., Pessoa, L., Desimone, R., &amp; Ungerleider, L. (2009).</p>

<p>The prefrontal cortex and the executive control of attention. Experimental Brain Research, 192(3), 489-497. Retrieved from http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00221-008-1642-z Ryding, E., BraÅdvik, B., &amp; Ingvar, D. H. (1996).</p>

<p>Silent speech activates prefrontal cortical regions asymmetrically, as well as speech-related areas in the dominant hemisphere. Brain and Language, 52(3), 435-451. doi:DOI: 10.1006/brln.1996.0023 Singh, J., &amp; Knight, R. T. (1990).</p>

<p>Frontal lobe contribution to voluntary movements in humans. Brain Research, 531(1-2), 45-54. doi:DOI: 10.1016/0006-8993(90)90756-2 Tanji, J., &amp; Hoshi, E. (2008).</p>

<p>Role of the lateral prefrontal cortex in executive behavioral control. Physiological Reviews, 88(1), 37-57. doi:10.1152/physrev.00014.2007 Tomita, H., Ohbayashi, M., Nakahara, K., Hasegawa, I., &amp; Miyashita, Y. (1999).</p>

<p>Top-down signal from prefrontal cortex in executive control of memory retrieval. Nature, 401(6754), 699-703. Retrieved from http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/44372 Weinberger, D. R., Berman, K. F., Zec, R. F., &amp; National Institute of Mental Health. (1986; 1986).</p>

<p>Physiologic dysfunction of dorsolateral prefrontal cortex in schizophrenia. Washington, D.C.: National Institute of Mental Health. White, I. M., &amp; Wise, S. P. (1999).</p>

<p>Rule-dependent neuronal activity in the prefrontal cortex. Experimental Brain Research, 126(3), 315-335. Retrieved from http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s002210050740</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flow, Education, and Ritalin: The Missing Link Between Addiction And Learning]]></title>
    <link href="http://timofei7.github.com/blog/2010/03/11/flow-and-education/"/>
    <updated>2010-03-11T22:10:37-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://timofei7.github.com/blog/2010/03/11/flow-and-education</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Flow, Education, and Ritalin</strong><br/>
My eyes are glued to the screen. They rarely blink. They become irritated but
I do not notice. I am in the zone. The force is with me. I feel it flow
through me. I am coding. Even though the coding paradigm may not apply to
everyone, we all know that feeling of hyper-attention. When an activity is so
engrossing that the rest of the world fades away, we are left mano-a-mano,
tête-à-tête, our ego and the task battling together for mutual gain.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>In positive psychology the term coined by Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi to describe
this is "flow". In his seminal work on flow, Csikszentmihalyi uses various
experiential self-report methods to study flow, and he has found some key
techniques that can help in achieving this state. However, he does not mention
the biological mechanisms behind flow. Examining this connection leads to some
interesting findings. If the brain functions during a state of flow include
the brain's attention pathways, then this likely implicates dopamine as one of
the brain chemicals through which flow is experienced. Dopamine is in part not
only responsible for regulating attention but is also the primary
neurotransmitter of reward. Is flow then a state of constant dopamine rush--a
stream of attention and reward causing a physical high? This would explain the
addictive nature of flow. Additionally we could then draw further powerful
conclusions about the utility of flow in our lives. Specifically a
relationship between flow and dopamine suggests further directions of research
relating flow to Ritalin and education. There are thus three main topics to
address in attempting to make a case that more research into this area would
be indispensable:</p>

<ol>
<li>What are the cognitive pathways involved in flow?</li>
<li>Is dopamine the cause of flow?</li>
<li>Is education a practical application for flow theory?
Understanding how flow happens and how it relates to attention and reward can
be potentially useful in developing new techniques for learning and also can
have broader significance such as in finding non-drug based treatments for
attention disorders.</li>
</ol>


<p><strong>What are the cognitive pathways involved in flow?</strong><br/>
Csikszentmihalyi (1990) defines flow as "an intrinsically motivated, task-
focused state characterized by full concentration, a change in the awareness
of time (e.g., time passing quickly), feelings of clarity and control, a
merging of action and awareness, and a lack of self-consciousness". He claims
that there are eight contributing factors to this feeling (p.49):</p>

<ol>
<li> A challenging activity which requires skills</li>
<li> The ability to concentrate on the task</li>
<li>The task has clear goals</li>
<li>There is immediate feedback</li>
<li>There is deep involvement in the task</li>
<li>There is a perception of control</li>
<li> Sense of self disappears</li>
<li>Sense of time is altered
The experience of these is so rewarding that people spend their lives in
search of activities that can cause it. Csikszentmihlyi studies flow using a
survey technique he invented called ESM (experiential sampling method). Over
the course of his experiments he has given thousands of participants beepers
that go off at random times during the day. The participants then record what
they are doing and answer a few questions about how they feel. He found that
the conditions necessary for a task to induce flow are that the task is
challenging but that the agent has the requisite skills to undertake it, and
that as the agent performs the task it remains interesting and provides
feedback so that the agent can experience reward. If the task is too difficult
the agent would feel stressed or anxious and if the task is too easy it would
lead to boredom.</li>
</ol>


<p>Given this definition of flow an analysis can be made of the cognitive tasks
involved. Most of the eight factors are either specific to the domain of the
task (such as the skills required) or are feelings evoked during the activity.
However, two are directly related to a cognitive ability. The ability to
concentrate on the task and to be deeply involved in it requires <em>attention</em>.</p>

<p>William James (1890) gives us the most widely used definition of attention:</p>

<blockquote><p>It is the taking possession by the mind, in clear and vivid form, of one out
of what seem several simultaneously possible objects or trains of thought.
Focalization, concentration, of consciousness are of its essence. It implies
withdrawal from some things in order to deal effectively with others, and is a
condition which has a real opposite in the confused, dazed, scatterbrained
state which in French is called distraction, and Zerstreutheit
[absentmindedness] in German. (pg. 403)</p></blockquote>

<p>This definition, in and of itself, is remarkably similar to that of flow. Flow
in part requires a singular type of attention. If all the right circumstances
are present and attention is engaged then flow happens. Neuroimaging has shown
that attention as a cognitive system is spread through several brain areas,
however higher level attention, also called executive control (not simply
visual attention), is located primarily in the frontal cortex (Miller, E. K.,
Cohen, J. D., 2001). Executive control is the system responsible for planning,
initiating behavior, inhibiting inappropriate responses, abstract thinking,
and attentional selection (Goswami, U., 2008). To be able to focus on
something the mind needs to be able to ignore irrelevant stimuli. During flow
the mind also needs to be able to initiate actions and plan the next move. The
effects of time altering and sense of self that Csikszentmihalyi mentions are
both correlated to this part of the brain as well.</p>

<p><strong>Is dopamine the cause of flow?</strong><br/>
It has been shown that the neurotransmitter dopamine is part of the attention
regulation system (Nieoullon, A. 2002). Dopamine is one of the primary
mechanisms in the brain's reward circuit and takes part in the inhibitory part
of executive control (pg. 63). Dopaminergic system deficiencies are often
cited as causing attention deficit hyperactivity disorder and the primary
treatment for ADHD is via drugs such as Ritalin (pg. 57). Ritalin is an
amphetamine derivative and is functionally similar to cocaine (Genetic Science
Learning Center, 2010). Its primary method of action is increasing the levels
of dopamine available in the brain. The principal effect of extra dopamine in
the brain is increased energy and improved attention. However, Ritalin is
often abused not only for the attention enhancing properties but also for the
cocaine like euphoria that can occur at higher doses. Conversely drugs that
treat schizophrenia are dopamine antagonists that by reducing the available
dopamine in the brain also reduce motivation and attention (pg. 72) and even
in some cases prevent all feelings of pleasure (anhedonia) (Surguladze, S. et
all 2002 pg. 451).</p>

<p>There is evidence that dopamine is essential to the mechanisms of creativity,
ideation, and learning. The dopamine pathway increases both arousal and goal-
directedness and at the same time decreases inhibition and suppresses
competing behaviors (Flaherty, A. W., 2005. pg. 149). To confirm the
connection between dopamine and attention, one particular study used Positron
Emission Tomography (PET) scanning -- dopamine receptors were tagged with
radio isotopes and the subjects were asked to perform working memory and
sustained attention tasks. The scans then showed if dopamine receptors were
activated during the tasks and in which brain areas (Aalto, S., Bruck, A.,
Laine,M., Någren, K., Rinne, J. O., 2005). One of the brain mechanisms
involved in all of this is a brain circuit that senses expected and unexpected
rewards and then signals (via dopamine) that we should learn from them (Arias-
Carrión, O.; Pöppel, E. 2007, pg. 486). This system is responsible for not
only gambling addictions but also for much of our unconscious goal-directed
motivation (pg. 484). For instance the dopamine reward and attention circuit
has also been shown to be integral in game playing (Koepp,M.J. et al. 1998).</p>

<p>It would be an oversimplification to say that dopamine alone was responsible
for all the feelings associated with flow. It is, however, fair to say that it
is strongly implicated given its crucial role in attention regulation, reward
and learning. This would suggest that flow is really those moments when the
brain is in a highly attentive state, when it is being rewarded constantly for
each action, and when it is learning at each of those reward moments. What
Csikszentmihalyi is offering in his book is a methodology for creating the
right circumstances to help facilitate this continuous cycle of
expectation/reward/learning that is suggested by the dopamine connection.</p>

<p><strong>Is education a practical application for flow theory?</strong><br/>
It is no wonder given the power of flow that Csikszentmihalyi has also turned
his attention to studying flow in educational settings. One of the essential
parts of flow is that the activity is <em>autotelic</em>, that is has intrinsic
motivation in and of itself (Csikszentmihalyi, M., 1990, pg. 67). Usually we
start an activity because of an external goal, however as we continue that
activity there is the possibility of starting to enjoy it for its own sake.
That is one of the preconditions for flow and it is also evident in the
learning patterns of toddlers -- for instance a child after just starting to
read will read everything in sight (pg. 130). However in the typical school
system flow is hindered by many factors: the distractions of the classroom,
the uneven skill level of the class, the anxiety inducing difficulty of
certain subjects and the boring simplicity of others. Therein lies the
difficulty of the educational system, how to teach unwilling unmotivated
students material that is either too hard or too easy in a setting that is
distracting.</p>

<p>Csikszentmihalyi proposes that the techniques of flow be used. His first
proposal is that students be given the initial extrinsic motivation by
example. Teachers who enjoy what they do most often have students who also
want that same enjoyment (pg. 133). Given a positive model, the next step is
to match the difficulty of the material with the abilities of the students. In
a large classroom this is a challenge that does not have a ready solution.
Finally, feedback needs to be immediate and learning tasks organized in
attainable steps (pg. 131). Eric Jensen (1995) has this message for teachers:</p>

<blockquote><p>Teaching in a way that encourages students to reach the flow state may be
one of the most important roles you have. In this state, learners are highly
internally motivated, and learning becomes enjoyable. Help learners reach flow
by setting up favorable conditions for it. [...] learning will likely be
stifled by a rigid structure. Keep challenge high but stress low. Let learners
set the pace while you provide the support. Have them design a complex project
that is personally relevant, and then vary the resources to keep the task
appropriate to their ability levels. Make it exciting; use teams, simulations,
technology, and deadlines while maintaining the appropriate levels of guidance
[...] (pg. 137).</p></blockquote>

<p>Hektner and Csikszentmihalyi (1996) say that "in order to maintain the
enjoyment of flow, people must continually engage in new challenges to match
their increasing skills, and they must perfect their skills to meet the
challenges" (p. 4). Csikszentmihalyi then proposes that some of the biggest
<em>dangers</em> to flow are an overemphasis on rules, evaluation, focus on
competition and the ensuing self-consciousness that arises from that
(Csikszentmihalyi, M., 1990, pg. 137). These unfortunately are staples in many
educational systems. Jensen (1995) goes so far as to call these methods <em>brain
antagonistic</em> in his practical book on brain-based teaching (pg. xiii).</p>

<p>It is at this point that dopamine enters the picture. As schools struggle with
students' attentional problems, pharmaceutical companies and modern psychiatry
have provided the answer in the form of dopamine increasing drugs. In 2005, 29
million prescriptions for Ritalin and related drugs were written, nearly 80
percent of them for children (Pettus, A., 2006). Regardless of whether ADHD
medications are over-prescribed or not, it is obvious that a problem exists.</p>

<p>There have been followup studies into flow and learning (Egbert, J., 2003)
showing that flow can exist in classroom settings and that it can be used to
achieve higher rates of self reported interest and energy (Rathunde, K.,
Csikszentmihalyi, M., 2005). In a comparison study of learning states in
traditional versus Montessori schools, Csikszentmihalyi found that optimal
experience (a term used to describe a positive, flow-inducing, learning state)
leads to more <em>undivided</em> interest in the material by the students (pg. 506).
A case may thus be made that flow techniques should be further studied not
only in the context of enhancing the school experience, but that innovative
methodology may be used to alleviate some of the need for amphetamines in
schools.</p>

<p>In 1933, John Dewey suggested that the best state of mind for learning is one
that is "playful and serious at the same time" (p. 286). Today one can
certainly imagine an educational setting where: the material is custom
tailored to each student's ability level, the teacher enjoys the material, and
in which the student, excited to learn, can engage with the material fully to
the point of losing track of time. In a traditional classroom this still seems
difficult to accomplish, even with all the techniques that Csikszentmihalyi
(2005) and Jensen (1995) mention. However there is no technological barrier to
design a system in which students learn through a technology (in a system that
automatically adjusts for difficulty like the one employed by the GRE test)
such that their minds can be optimally activated. Brain antagonistic models of
learning have shown themselves to be problematic at best and in the search for
a new methodology perhaps flow theory can provide some insight into the
problem of attention and motivation in students.</p>

<p>The correlation between flow and dopamine shows us an area ready for further
exploration. If the techniques of flow elicit a type of dopamine high, then
studying these methods may provide answers to attentional disorders. This can
also drive the realization that the mechanisms behind creative passion are
similar to the mechanisms of cocaine addiction, and that can perhaps help find
answers to what pushes people toward one or the other or both. Learning can
and should be <em>joyful</em> (Wolk, S., 2008) and <em>addicting</em>, flow and dopamine
shows us a way to make it so.</p>

<hr />

<p>References:</p>

<p>Aalto, S., Bruck, A., Laine, M., Nagren, K., &amp; Rinne, J. O.
(2005). Frontal and temporal dopamine release during working memory and
attention tasks in healthy humans: A positron emission tomography study using
the high-affinity dopamine D2 receptor ligand [11C]FLB 457. Journal of
Neuroscience, 25(10), 2471-2477. doi:10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2097-04.2005</p>

<p>Arias-Carrión, O., &amp; Pöppel, E. (2007). Dopamine, learning and reward-seeking
behavior. Acta Neurobiol Exp, 67(4), 481-488.</p>

<p>Csikszentmihalyi, M. (1990). Literacy and intrinsic motivation. Daedalus,
119(2, Literacy in America), 115-140. Retrieved from
http://www.jstor.org/stable/20025303</p>

<p>Csikszentmihalyi, M. (1991; 1990). Flow :The psychology of optimal experience.
New York: HarperPerennial.</p>

<p>Dewey, J. (1933). How we think. D. C. Heath, Boston.</p>

<p>Egbert, J. (2003). A study of flow theory in the foreign language classroom.
The Modern Language Journal, 87(4), 499-518. doi:10.1111/1540-4781.00204</p>

<p>Flaherty, A. W. (2005). Frontotemporal and dopaminergic control of idea
generation and creative drive. The Journal of Comparative Neurology, 493(1),
147-153. doi:10.1002/cne.20768</p>

<p>Genetic Science Learning Center. (2010, March 10). Ritalin and cocaine: The
connection and the controversy. Retrieved March 10, 2010, from
http://learn.genetics.utah.edu/content/addiction/issues/ritalin.html</p>

<p>Goswami, U. (2008). Cognitive development: The learning brain New York, NY,
US: Psychology Press.</p>

<p>Hektner, J., &amp; Csikszentmihalyi, M. (1996). A longitudinal exploration of flow
and intrinsic motivation in adolescents. Paper presented at the annual meeting
of the American Educational Research Association, New York.</p>

<p>James, W. (1981). The principles of psychology. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard
University Press.</p>

<p>Jensen, E. (2008). Brain-based learning :The new paradigm of teaching (2nd
ed.). Thousand Oaks, CA.: Corwin Press.</p>

<p>Koepp, M. J., Gunn, R. N., Lawrence, A. D., Cunningham, V. J., Dagher, A.,
Jones, T., et al. (1998). Evidence for striatal dopamine release during a
video game. Nature, 393(6682), 266-268. Retrieved from
http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/30498</p>

<p>Miller, E. K., &amp; Cohen, J. D. (2001). An integrative theory of prefrontal
cortex function. Annual Review of Neuroscience, 24(1), 167-202. Retrieved from
http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.neuro.24.1.167</p>

<p>Morgan, H. (2004). Real learning :A bridge to cognitive neuroscience (1st
ed.). Lanham, Md.: ScarecrowEducation.</p>

<p>Nieoullon, A. (2002). Dopamine and the regulation of cognition and attention.
Progress in Neurobiology, 67(1), 53-83. doi:DOI: 10.1016/S0301-0082(02)00011-4</p>

<p>Pettus, A. (2006, July-August 2006). Psychiatry By prescription: Do
psychotropic drugs blur the boundaries between illness and health? Harvard
Magazine. Retrieved from http://harvardmagazine.com/2006/07/psychiatry-by-
prescripti.html</p>

<p>Posner, M. I., &amp; Petersen, S. E. (1990). The attention system of the human
brain. Annual Review of Neuroscience, 13(1), 25-42. Retrieved from http://arjo
urnals.annualreviews.org/doi/abs/10.1146/annurev.ne.13.030190.000325</p>

<p>Rathunde, K., &amp; Csikszentmihalyi, M. (2005). Middle school students'
motivation and quality of experience: A comparison of montessori and
traditional school environments. American Journal of Education, 111(3),
341-371. Retrieved from http://www.jstor.org/stable/3566831</p>

<p>Schiefele, U., &amp; Csikszentmihalyi, M. (1995). Motivation and ability as
factors in mathematics experience and achievement. Journal for Research in
Mathematics Education, 26(2), 163-181. Retrieved from
http://www.jstor.org/stable/749208</p>

<p>Surguladze, S., Keedwell, P., &amp; Phillips, M. (2003). Neural systems underlying
affective disorders. Advances in Psychiatric Treatment, 9(6), 446-455.
doi:10.1192/apt.9.6.446</p>

<p>Wise, R. A. (2004). Dopamine, learning and motivation. Nature Reviews.
Neuroscience, 5(6), 483-494. Retrieved from http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrn1406</p>

<p>Wolk, S. (2008, September 2008). Joy in school. Educational Leadership, 66,
8-15. Retrieved from http://www.ascd.org/publications/educational_leadership/s
ept08/vol66/num01/Joy_in_School.aspx</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Moment in the Life of Camus' Sisyphus]]></title>
    <link href="http://timofei7.github.com/blog/2010/02/28/a-moment-in-the-life-of-camus-sisyphus/"/>
    <updated>2010-02-28T22:30:47-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://timofei7.github.com/blog/2010/02/28/a-moment-in-the-life-of-camus-sisyphus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I watch my cursed boulder tumble down my mountain. I heave a sigh of relief;
my aching muscles allowed a brief respite. As I stand on its majestic craggy
peak, I survey my mountain beneath me. My boulder is now far out of sight, but
I can feel it down below in the darkness waiting for me. I send my thoughts
out to it -- my boulder you are my work, my affliction, my friend and my
enemy. I shall see you soon enough. In these seemingly countless days,
logically countable but practically indistinguishable, my mind is not always
so clear. At this instant I am aware -- tomorrow I may not be. I grasp the
moment, tenderly. Let me slow it down and take joy in my thoughts. Before my
curse -- I can barely remember -- I took my thoughts for granted. Mortal, I
had a limited amount of time for thoughts, yet I did not enjoy them. Immortal,
and now each thought is precious -- I have forever and thus have infinite
thoughts, yet I take joy in each, insignificant as it is. The absurdity
continues, the one constant along with my rock and my mountain to keep me
company. Yet as I stand there, the cold rare mountain air turning my breath
visible, I am happy.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I remember the moment when first I became fully conscious of my eternal
meaninglessness -- the horror I felt. With time I came to understand that my
previous life, filled with hopes and dreams, was as absurd as my rock and
mountain world. I lied to myself then in order to avoid becoming conscious of
the true nature of existence. Now I have no such luxury, the stark landscape,
unchanging except through my actions, reminds me continually of the futility
of my labor.</p>

<p>Mercury says that Camus once wrote about me, "His fate belongs to him."<sup>1</sup> He
calls me an "absurd hero."<sup>2</sup>  I now accept this role. My existence is an
analogy for the futility of rebellion -- there is no escape from the absurd. I
have no hope of completion and no hope of a purpose. Hope would be a lie -- I
can not console myself with lies. In my acknowledgment of my own
ridiculousness I find freedom. I am free to experience, to find joy within
myself or to not, and I am free to create my own happiness, even while I am
not free from the binds of my curse.</p>

<p>Another mortal writes, "Because there is no absolute certainty to which to
turn, each person must discover ultimate purpose on his or her own."<sup>3</sup> Is my
revolt in spite of meaninglessness my purpose? More often than not I get so
caught up in the pure action of my task, nothing else about my condition
matters. However, I have accepted that although the task is itself futile, I
am free to enjoy it. The feeling of my body straining against the massive
weight, navigating the treacherous terrain, my ragged breath, the pulsing of
my immortal heart, these things I look forward to. This world is my creation.
By my actions I define it. It is my flesh and blood and thought, and thus my
purpose.</p>

<p>I listen to my breathing. I start my descent down my beloved hated mountain.
My parting thought at Camus is this: He should not use me as an example of an
"absurd hero," as by that action he gives my existence semblance of meaning.
He takes away my freedom to pursue my own meaning. Is his "absurdity" the lack
of knowledge of the bigger context or the knowledge that any bigger context is
meaningless? If the context of my existence is a persistent analogy for
absurdity then it might cease itself to be absurd. Perhaps Camus was simply
ignorant of the larger context of his existence as a tiny thread in the cloth
of existence, locally appearing insignificant but with ripples of continuity
that pervade everything.</p>

<p>Camus maintains that it is an <em>ascesis</em> to be an absurd creator. This I can
understand. I lean into my burden, striving for the purpose of striving or for
the purpose of illustration, either way happy to be reunited with my boulder.</p>

<p>notes</p>

<p>1 Camus, A. (1964). The myth of Sisyphus,and other essays. New York: A.A.
Knopf. (pg. 123)</p>

<p>2 Ibid. (pg. 120)</p>

<p>3 Csikszentmihalyi, M. (1991; 1990). Flow :The psychology of optimal
experience. New York: HarperPerennial. (pg. 225)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[assignment: write about where I see myself in x number of years]]></title>
    <link href="http://timofei7.github.com/blog/2010/02/19/assignment-write-about-where-i-see-myself-in-x-number-of-years/"/>
    <updated>2010-02-19T21:53:28-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://timofei7.github.com/blog/2010/02/19/assignment-write-about-where-i-see-myself-in-x-number-of-years</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Instead of writing seriously, I wrote an imaginary interview. BTW:Living in a
van... happened in real life; C.com/"light goop" ...well it was supposed to be
about the future!</p>

<p><strong>FRAMBERG MAGAZINE INTERVIEW (Issue: March, 2018)</strong><br/>
<strong>Today we interview Tim Tregubov,  one of the visionaries behind a small company that might just be changing the way we interact with the world.  C.com is responsible for MultiPhen technology and the company is developing promising new applications that will further integrate adaptive intelligent systems with <em>the human system</em>.  The company is being heralded as a forerunner of a new type of business model which they are calling <em>engaged activism</em>.   We will find out what makes him tick, what C.com is all about and how it originated.</strong></p>

<!--more-->


<p><em><strong>Framberg:</strong> So you are one of the founders of C.com? </em></p>

<p><strong>Tim:</strong> Yep. Although it wasn't like we just had a great brainstorming session and out popped a company.  In fact I'd say c.com isn't a company at all, and it is my hope that it never will be!</p>

<p>It started as just a group of friends pulling allnighters in a computer lab at
college.   We made a good team and had a blast doing it.  Then we all
graduated and got "real" jobs.  We ended up working cold rainy nights sitting
in front of computers in cubicles doing other peoples' bidding.  The good
times were just a memory.  Many years later, we'd get laid-off from our jobs
at the big corporations to be replaced by new dream-filled youth -- youth just
as ready as we were to give up their dreams, creativity and energy in exchange
for job security.</p>

<p><em><strong>Framberg: </strong> So what happened, that's not the end of the story right?</em></p>

<p>Tim: Not at all.  In fact, that never happened!  If it had happened, c.com
never would have even been a twinkle in our eyes. I say this as a warning to
anybody who has had an idea but wants to put it off in favor of making some
money first.  Don't put the golden handcuffs on, rather grab your friends,
grab your idea and sprint out onto the playing field.  If there is one time in
your life when you should do this it is now, not later.</p>

<p>So what really happened was that we kept trying ideas.  My ideas were always a
bit grandiose and self involved but they were cute.  I have always been an
excitable person and tend to dive right into an idea.  Not being a great
swimmer I tend to cannonball.  This sets off lots of waves and people get wet.
Diving right into this analogy -- this would whet their appetite. Sometimes
one of the ideas would spin off an idea wave that we could surf.  This is not
to say all the ideas were mine -- I'm going to get beat up back at the office
for this.</p>

<p><em><strong>Framberg:</strong> Why do you say that c.com isn't a company? What is it?</em></p>

<p><strong>Tim:</strong> c.com is really more of a family.  If you prefer the word company we insist on the older interpretation of the word -- the theater company -- the company of companionship.  The organizational structure of c.com is less of an 'inc' and more of a fellowship.  This sort of company is based around the passion of the founders.  There are no employees per se, everybody is an owner. There is no boss.  We only work on projects we really love. We don't compromise our projects for investors or clients but work for the love of the thing rather than for the monetizing of it.  From the beginning we knew we didn't want to be VC controlled vaporware. What is our mission?  Simple. Create.</p>

<p><em><strong>Framberg:</strong>  Just to create?  Isn't the company involved in certain
particular areas?</em></p>

<p><strong>Tim: </strong> It isn't "just"!   We create because it is imperative.  Your readers have perhaps heard of the existential maxim "existence precedes essence."  We have a duty to create the world as we believe it should be. So it isn't just lighthearted play. I believe strongly that once we realize that we are completely responsible for the world, and that by each of our actions we define the world, in part, according to our wishes -- then it becomes clear that our actions do not simply exist in a void and certainly are not just harmless. Quite the contrary.  In fact, every action has meaning and at c.com we strive toward having a socially positive impact on the world.  Every project we undertake has a socially positive foundation.  Whether it is a new educational toy for improving math skills in preschoolers or a social network to promote micro-philanthropy for schools in Ghana, all our projects at their core try to focus on improving the human condition.</p>

<p><em><strong>Framberg: </strong> That is quite a philosophical underpinning for a company! Is
this what you call engaged activism? Those sound like lofty ideals, but how do
you manage in practice?</em></p>

<p><strong>Tim:</strong> Yeah, this is definitely a part of <em>engaged activism</em>.  When we started we had two main goals. One was to do work which we personally found engaging.  In the lab we would pull allnighters not because we had to but because we were in the zone. We were fully "into" our work. We also enjoyed each others' company.  So our primary motivation was "engaging work with cool people."</p>

<p>Our second tenet was that our work had to be meaningful.  We wanted to
contribute to society and be able to believe in what we were striving toward.
So our secondary motivation was "socially positive projects that we all could
believe in."  Most importantly we didn't want to simply donate some part of
our profits to good causes, we actually wanted our projects to be good causes
themselves!  If you are working with people you like, on a project you believe
in, and the work itself is rewarding then you are addicted and fulfilled and
happy.</p>

<p><em><strong>Framberg:</strong> What about creature comforts though?  What about money?</em></p>

<p><strong>Tim: </strong> When we started we all worked for free.  We lived in our parents' basements or at our friends' houses.  We worked nights and we barely scraped by.  We were happy.  I believe that the usual things people work toward, money/fame/success/comfort, can all be side effects of impassioned work.  If we loved what we did and put that love into our work then this would be recognized and appreciated.  This was all secondary to the actual fulfillment of the work itself.</p>

<p><em><strong>Framberg:</strong>  Are you happier now that you have achieved some success?</em></p>

<p><strong>Tim:</strong>  I wouldn't say that the success has any bearing on my happiness.  I was happy homeless and I am happy now.  We have cooler toys in the office though now, and with the added success we can create better more interesting things.</p>

<p><em><strong>Framberg:</strong>  Homeless?  Would you like to share that story?</em></p>

<p><strong>Tim: </strong> [Laughs] In college one summer I lived in a van.  It was my parents' van and I pimped it out so I wasn't exactly being homeless.  I was however a bit persecuted by the campus police and had to park discreetly at night.  Some nights I spent in the Walmart parking lot. I showered at the computer science building, so it was really actually rather comfortable.</p>

<p><em><strong>Framberg: </strong> So tell us more about yourself.  When you are not living in a
van what do you do in your free time?</em></p>

<p><strong>Tim:</strong>  Free time?  Mostly I hang out at the studio.  That is what we call the office. I also hike a lot and spend time with the family.  I have an 8 month old daughter, Anki, we hang out at the studio together all the time.  She is a genius in the making I can tell.  Her favorite toy right now is this really expensive prototype "light goop".  It glows and changes color depending on the shape it is in.  It is not yet practical to mass produce, but she loves being the only one in the world with one.</p>

<p><em><strong>Framberg:</strong> Is that a MultiPhen technology?</em></p>

<p><strong>Tim:</strong>  All of our tech is MultiPhen these days.</p>

<p><em><strong>Framberg:</strong>  What is MultiPhen exactly?</em></p>

<p><strong>Tim:</strong>  We don't rightly know ourselves.  Actually, it is simply a buzzword I came up with to call our technology.  We were making things that interacted at multiple levels and exhibits multiple phenomenons?   MultiPhen simply sounded cool.   People love buzzwords.</p>

<p><em><strong>Framberg: </strong> We suspected that was the case all along.  It sounds like you
are a bit of a free thinker.  Have you always been a rebel?  Did that help you
get to where you are?</em></p>

<p><strong>Tim:</strong>  I wouldn't say I am a rebel.  [Laughs] I have not had a traditional path though.  My life used to be controlled by fear.  It made me not take the traditional path to college when I should have, instead I tried to start my own web design business after high school and failed.  Then I worked as a programmer for a short while and then as a sysadmin at the college where I eventually started taking classes, and even more eventually graduated from.  That experience changed me quite a bit, I became braver and started moving through life faster.  Went to grad school right after that and started c.com.</p>

<p>I've learned a lot from my mistakes.  It is unfortunate that wisdom cannot be
taught but must be learned from experience.  I know that my strange background
has helped make me who I am and I do not regret it.  I only wish that I had
gained the wisdom of how to be braver and happier earlier.  I still like to do
things a bit differently, but now it is a choice and partially an affectation
-- I am much less subject to the anxieties that plagued me when I was younger.
This path of discovery, though, made me open to learning and exploring and
playing at points in my life when other people were concentrating on other
things.  I think I was fairly self-restricted as a teen, more so than is
normal, but as the years went by I became more internally free and
rediscovered that play and energy of childhood.  A lot of what I have achieved
has been due to this process of discovery.</p>

<p><em><strong>Framberg:</strong> What is in store in the future for you personally?</em></p>

<p><strong>Tim: </strong> That is a good question.  More of the same!  In college I took a class that brought up the question of happiness and one thing that we did in the class was identify our main strengths.  My top five strengths were creativity, curiosity, love of learning, energy and appreciation of beauty.  As long as I am able to express my strengths and believe that I am making a positive contribution to the world, then I am happy.   My family, my friends and c.com have enabled me to live the good life so far.  I hope I am up for the challenge of raising my daughter and future little c.com'ers.  That is my next big life challenge.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
